Pima County, Arizona records 1864-1923 (bulk 1867-1904)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Pima County, Arizona records, 1864-1923 (bulk 1867-1904)
AZ 083
Pima County (Ariz.)
Financial accounts, petitions, bonds, reports, leases, deeds, abstracts of titles, tax lists, bids, and correspondence related to Pima County operations. Chiefly records of the Board of Supervisors, such as letterpress copies of correspondence, petitions for appointments to county office, and financial demands and warrants.
21 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL:http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Historical Note
Pima County, located in southern Arizona, was formed in 1864 by an act of the First Legislative Session of the Territory of Arizona. The county seat is Tucson, Arizona.
Organization
This collection is organized into ten series:
Series I: Board of Supervisors, 1864-1908
Series II: Assessor, 1875-1923
Series III: Justice Court, 1867-1897
Series IV: District Court, 1867-1903
Series V: Miscellaneous (part 1), 1864-1904
Series VI: School District, 1867-1905
Series VII: Miscellaneous (part 2), 1864-1884
Series VIII: Tax Collector, 1871-1875
Series IX: Treasurer, 1865-1896
Series X: Election Returns, 1864-1902
Scope and Content Note
Financial accounts, petitions, bonds, reports, leases, deeds, abstracts of titles, tax lists, bids, and correspondence related to Pima County operations. Chiefly records of the Board of Supervisors, such as letterpress copies of correspondence, petitions for appointments to county office, and financial demands and warrants. Other Board records include 1879 orders to incorporate the villages of Tombstone and Arivaca, and papers related to the construction of the first and second County courthouses. Assessor records consist of correspondence and a 1900-1907 block book.
School records include financial records, correspondence, and reports. Teachers' monthly reports indicate number of students enrolled; reports for Florence, 1873, and Tres Alamos, 1874-1875, give student names. School census reports, 1874-1904, list student names, race, whether native or foreign born, and parents' names. Records of other county offices are from the Justice Court, District Court, Coroner, County Hospital, Jailer, Sheriff, Treasurer, and Election Office. A Probate Court docket dates from 1883 to 1885, and an Arizona tax list is for 1879.
Some records relate to bonds for County services such as road overseers, constables, justices of the peace, butchers, physicians, and provisions for indigent sick and prisoners. Also present are records of the Calabasas, Tucson, and Northwestern Railroad Co., 1885-1886, 1892; also the Tucson and Gulf of California Railroad, 1882-1884.
Note: A more detailed inventory of boxes 17-19 and box 37 is available at the repository.
Access Terms
Calabasas, Tucson, and Northwestern Railroad
Tucson and Gulf of California Railroad
School census -- Arizona -- Pima County -- History -- Sources
Elections -- Arizona -- Pima County -- History -- Sources
Pima County (Ariz.) -- History -- Sources
Tucson (Ariz.) -- History -- Sources
Arizona -- History -- To 1912 -- Sources
Census
Correspondence
Petitions
Reports
Container List
- Finding aid for the collection. (Box 1)
- Series I: Board of Supervisors, 1864-1908
  - Board of Supervisors: Demands on the Treasury. 1864-1871, 1873 (Box 2)
    Records include financial accounts, both allowed and disallowed, covering court fees, sheriff's fees, rents, office supplies, salaries, jail supplies and services, printing, doctor's fees for care of indigents and prisoners, etc.
  - Board of Supervisors: Demands on the Treasury. 1874-1876 (Box 3)
  - Board of Supervisors: Demands on the Treasury. 1877-1879 (Box 4)
  - Board of Supervisors: Demands on the Treasury. 1880-1882 (Box 5)
  - Board of Supervisors: Demands on the Treasury. 1883-1888 (Box 6)
  - Board of Supervisors: Demands on the Treasury. 1889-April 1890 (Box 7)
  - Board of Supervisors: Demands on the Treasury. May-December 1890 (Box 8)
  - Board of Supervisors: Demands on the Treasury. 1891 (Box 9)
  - Board of Supervisors: Demands on the Treasury. 1892-1893, 1895, 1899-1900 (Box 10)
  - Board of Supervisors: Demands on the Treasury. 1901-November 1903 (Box 11)
  - Board of Supervisors: Demands on the Treasury. December 1903-September 1905 (Box 12)
  - Board of Supervisors: Demands on the Treasury. October 1905-April 3, 1908 (Box 13)
  - Board of Supervisors: Demands on the Treasury. April 4-July 1908 (Box 14)
  - Board of Supervisors: Warrants and Stubs. 1864-1865, 1867-1880 (Box 15)
  - Board of Supervisors: Warrants and stubs. 1881-1885, 1887, 1892, 1895-1901, 1903-1905, 1907-1908 (Box 16)
  - Board of Supervisors: Letters, petitions and reports to the Board. 1865, 1867-1881, 1884, 1886-1888 (Box 17)
  - Board of Supervisors: Letters, petitions and reports to the Board. 1889-1894 (Box 18)
  - Board of Supervisors: Letters, petitions and reports to the Board. 1895-1898, 1900-1903, No Date (Box 19)
  - From Allen, John B. (Chairman of the Board), order for Peter R. Brady, Sheriff, to rent from Mark Aldrich certain buildings on Military Plaza for county offices. February 16, 1867 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Lease between Mark Aldrich and Pima County Board of Supervisors for rent of certain buildings on Military Plaza for use as county offices. March 28, 1867 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Order of Board of Supervisors regarding transfer of San Rafael del Valle land grant. April 3, 1877 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - From Osborn, William J. (Clerk of the Board of Supervisors), notice of meeting called to discuss establishment of a public road from Tucson via Davidson Canyon, Empire Ranch, Crittenden, etc. October 8, 1879 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - From Oury, William S. (Clerk of the Board of Supervisors), communication regarding the construction of a bridge across the San Pedro River at Charleston (copy). December 29, 1880 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - From Martin, James (of St. Louis), affidavit relating to loss of warrants. June 25, 1887 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - From Lacy, H. (Chairman of the Board), order for a special meeting of the Board. April 8, 1890 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Transcript of proceedings before the Board of Equalization of Taxes regarding assessment of Santa Rita Land and Cattle Company for 1891. July 14, 1891 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Assessment list in the handwriting of Lionel M. Jacobs. No Date (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Two sketches for "forms and notice for mortgages," in the handwriting of Lionel M. Jacobs. No Date (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Commitments to the County Hospital. 1876, 1880-1881 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Orders to incorporate the villages of Tombstone and Arivaca. November 1, 1879 and December 20, 1879 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Orders to Tax Collector, regarding assessments, and to Treasurer, regarding transfer of county funds. 1889-1890 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Papers relating to the construction of the first and second Pima County Court Houses, and the various additions to same. 1867-1899 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    Includes bids, deed from Mark Aldrich for land, articles of agreement between the Board and Charles Meyers for construction, notice of completion and establishment of offices, specifications for re-roofing and bids for same, articles of agreement for construction of additional rooms, and similar papers dealing with the construction of the second Court House in 1881.
  - Requisitions to the Board for office supplies and equipment. 1877, 1879, 1887-1893 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Certificates of audit. 1895-1897 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Board of Supervisors: Letterpress copies of correspondence, forms sent out, reports to various territorial officials, assessment lists, etc. January 1885-February 1888 (Box 21)
    Also contains correspondence of the Board of Equalization.
  - Board of Supervisors: Letterpress copies of correspondence, etc. March 1888-June 1890. (Box 22)
  - Board of Supervisors: Letterpress copies of correspondence, etc. July 1890-August 1891 (Box 23)
  - Board of Supervisors: Letterpress copies of correspondence, etc. June 1891-March 17, 1893 (Box 24)
  - Board of Supervisors: Letterpress copies of correspondence, etc. March 20, 1893-October 10, 1894 (Box 25)
  - Board of Supervisors: Letterpress copies of correspondence, etc. October 11, 1894-April 16, 1898 (Box 26)
  - Board of Supervisors: Letterpress copies of correspondence, etc. April 16, 1898-May 23, 1899 (Box 27)
  - Board of Supervisors: Letterpress copies of correspondence, etc. May 24-December 1899 (Box 28)
- Series II: Assessor, 1875-1923
  - Assessor: Statement under oath of the property held, owned, claimed by, or in possession of, for the year. 1875-1881 (Box 29)
  - Assessor: Correspondence. 1888-1889, 1892, 1895, 1902-1909, 1914, 1919-1923 (Box 30)
  - Assessor: Letterpress copies of correspondence and tax notices. June 1892-August 1894, June 1897 (Box 31)
  - Assessor: Tax list and other records. 1879-1880 (Box 32)
    Contains a record of sale of horses and mules by the sheriff, April 9, 1880
  - Assessor: Block book. 1900-1907 (Box 33)
    Includes documentation of Buell's Addition, South Side University Addition, Sunny Side Addition, Buena Vista Addition, Canfield Tract, Manlove Addition.
- Series III: Justice Court, 1867-1897
  - Justice Court: Commitments. 1867-1880 (Box 34)
  - Justice Court: Discharges. 1869-1881 (Box 35, Folder 1-2)
  - Justice Court: Executions. 1870, 1874-1875, 1877, 1881 (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - Justice Court: Inquisitions. 1867, 1877 (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - Justice Court: Judgements. 1869, 1876 (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - Justice Court: Reports of cases tried. 1875-1876, 1879 (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Justice Court: Reports of fines. 1871, 1894-1897 (Box 35, Folder 7)
  - Justice Court: Summons. 1867, 1873-1874, 1876-1877 (Box 35, Folder 8)
  - Justice Court: Undertakings. 1869, 1874 (Box 35, Folder 9)
  - Justice Court: Warrants for arrest. 1867-1874, 1878-1879 (Box 35, Folder 10)
  - Justice Court: Writs of Attachments. 1873-1874, 1877, 1881 (Box 35, Folder 11)
  - Justice Court: Miscellaneous. (Box 35, Folder 12)
- Series IV: District Court, 1864-1903
  - District Court: Miscellaneous documents. 1867, 1869-1877, 1879-1880, 1891, 1893, 1896-1897, 1900 (Box 36, Folder 1-3)
  - District Court: Case of Santiago Ainsa, administrator of estate of Frank Ely (deceased) vs. New Mexico and Arizona Railroad Company (transcript). 1892 (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - District Court: Case of Frank Dobszinsky vs. H. E. Jenkins and H. D. Jenkins (transcript). 1890 (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - District Court: Case of John L. Stevens vs. Morgan R. Wise (transcript). 1899 (Box 36, Folder 6)
  - District Court: Case of City of Tucson vs. Lizzie Woods, et al. Regarding removal of the "wedge" on Congress Street. (Order appointing a commission, and assessment roll). 1903 (Box 36, Folder 7)
  - District Court: Case of United States of America vs. Colin Cameron. Regarding fencing of public lands (transcript). 1887 (Box 36, Folder 8)
  - District Court: Case of C. M. Williams vs. San Pedro Cattle Company (transcript). 1894 (Box 36, Folder 9)
- Series V: Miscellaneous (part 1), 1866-1904
  - Abstracts of titles to various mines including Dragoon, Tom Scott, Defiance, Bell and Challenge. March 10, 1880 (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Agreements and Bonds. 1871-1878, 1880-1882, 1887-1889, 1892, 1895, 1897, 1903 (Box 37, Folder 2-4)
    Note: A more detailed inventory of agreements and bonds is available at the repository.
  - Assessor: Personal property tax collected. April-May 1887 (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - Invoices from Pima County to the U. S. Government for rent of a room in the county Court House, for use during federal court proceedings. 1872-1876 (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - Bonds relating to court actions. 1870-1877 (Box 37, Folder 7)
    Includes:
    Bond in suit of Thomas Harmon against Mortimer R. Platt, 1870
    Bond of indemnity to William S. Oury, Sheriff, in suit of Barnett and Block against Zubiate and Company, 1873
    Bond of indemnity to Will S. Oury, Sheriff, in suit of Wormser and Wertheimer against Zubriate and Company, 1873
    Bond of indemnity to William S. Oury, Sheriff, in suit of Woffenden against Goldbert and Company, 1873
    Redelivery bond in suit of Joseph Neugass against A. Brichta, 1877
  - Calabasas, Tucson, and Northwestern Railroad Company: Miscellaneous documents. 1885-1886, 1892 (Box 37, Folder 8)
    Includes names of incorporators, notice of election to vote about granting county aid and various petitions to issue bonds, secure county aid, extend completion time of the railroad.
  - Census of Pima County. 1867 (Box 37, Folder 9)
  - Certificates of nomination. 1902, 1904 (Box 37, Folder 10)
  - Coroner: Miscellaneous documents. 1867, 1869, 1875 (Box 37, Folder 11)
  - County Hospital: Report of patients under treatment and remaining in the hospital. October-December 1899 (Box 37, Folder 12)
  - Deeds. 1876-1884 (Box 37, Folder 13)
    Sheriff's deeds under execution, relating to various land grants
    Quitclaim deed from Pima County to Manuel Gandora: Calabasas and Tumacacori Land Grant
    Deed, bargain and sale from Alfred Green to Mary Harrison for property in La Noria
  - Delinquent Taxes. 1867-1900 (Box 37, Folder 14)
    Includes receipts and reports by the Sheriff, Treasurer, District Attorney and Tax Collector.
  - Goldschmidt, Leo: Various papers transferring certain notes and other evidence of indebtedness to Albert Steinfeld. 1889 (Box 37, Folder 15)
  - Governor: Election proclamations. 1878-1904 (Box 37, Folder 16)
    October 5, 1878: John C. Fremont, accompanied by a letter
    September 25, 1902: Alexander O. Brodie
    October 28, 1903: Alexander O. Brodie (5 copies)
    September 15 and October 31, 1904: Alexander O. Brodie
  - Governor: Extradition orders. 1876 (Box 37, Folder 17)
  - Governor: Pardons. 1871-1874, 1876, 1879-1880 (Box 37, Folder 18)
  - Jailor (Tucson and Nogales): Reports. 1875, 1881, 1887-1890 (Box 38, Folder 1)
    Includes regular reports, record of U. S. prisoners in the Pima County Jail and testimony regarding the escape of prisoners on January 1, 1875.
  - Jury Lists. 1872, 1874-1878, 1880 (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Mining claims: Notices of location. 1874-1875, 1877-1878 (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - Parsons, Mary E. (school teacher from Cambridge, Massachusetts): Letter to Governor A. P. K. Safford. June 23, 1873 (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - Probate Court: Miscellaneous papers and documents. 1864, 1867, 1872, 1874, 1877-1881, 1884 (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - Recorder: Miscellaneous papers and documents. 1870-1874, 1876, 1878, 1880, 1882, 1886, 1903 (Box 38, Folder 6)
  - Recorder's Court: Miscellaneous papers and documents. 1873-1874 (Box 38, Folder 7)
  - Road Overseers: Miscellaneous financial records. 1871-1888 (Box 38, Folder 8)
  - Sheriff (and/or Assessor): Miscellaneous financial records. 1868-1887 (Box 38, Folder 9)
  - Sheriff: Receipts. 1868-1869, 1871, 1887, 1897 (Box 38, Folder 10)
  - Sheriff: Miscellaneous documents. 1866, 1873-1879, 1881, 1887, 1895 (Box 38, Folder 11)
  - Sheriff: Monthly report of property taxes collected. September-November 1871 (Box 38, Folder 12)
  - Sheriff: Monthly reports of License taxes collected. 1864-1892 (Box 38, Folder 13)
  - Statement under oath of ore extracted from mines. 1880 (Box 38, Folder 14)
  - Supreme Court Chief Justice: Miscellaneous documents. 1874, 1894 (Box 38, Folder 15)
  - Tax Collector: Certificate of sale for real estate. March-April 1899 (Box 38, Folder 16)
  - Tax Collector: Monthly report. 1897 (Box 38, Folder 17)
  - Territorial Prison Superintendent: Receipts for prisoners. 1875-1876 (Box 38, Folder 18)
  - Territorial Treasurer: Receipts and accounts regarding county funds due the Territorial treasury. 1865, 1868-1871, 1876-1877, 1896, 1900-1901 (Box 38, Folder 19)
  - Treasurer: Reports to the Superintendent of Schools regarding school funds. 1889-1893 (Box 38, Folder 20)
  - Treasurer: Miscellaneous documents. 1874-1875, 1890 (Box 38, Folder 21)
  - U. S. Commissioner: Document regarding a case of mail robbery. 1878 (Box 38, Folder 22)
- Series VI: School District, 1867-1905
  - Schools: Financial records. 1867, 1871-1876 (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - Schools: Joint County Institutes, attendance of teachers. 1894, 1897 (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - Schools: Miscellaneous school documents. 1872-1873, 1875, 1887-1891, 1893-1895, 1898-1899 (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - Schools: Correspondence from Osburn, William J. (Superintendent of Schools). 1873-1874 (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - Schools: Apportionments of school funds. 1890-1893, 1897-1898 (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - Schools: Superintendent of Schools report to Territorial Board of Examiners. 1887-1888, 1892-1894, 1896-1898 (Box 39, Folder 6)
  - Schools: Superintendent of Schools annual report to the Governor. 1873-1874 (Box 39, Folder 7)
  - Schools: Superintendent of Schools quarterly report to the Board of Supervisors of warrants drawn upon the School Fund. 1887-1888 (Box 39, Folder 8)
  - Schools: Teacher's annual report of the public school. 1893-1894, 1896-1897, 1898-1899, 1899-1900 (Box 39, Folder 9)
  - Schools: Tucson School District notice of special election regarding tax to be levied to build a public school house; also a poll list and tally list. June 21, 1873 (Box 39, Folder 10)
  - Schools: Trustees' reports 1874, 1895-1896 (Box 39, Folder 11)
  - Schools: Warrants for supplies. 1892 (Box 39, Folder 12)
  - Schools: Warrants for salaries, services, etc. 1873-1880, 1883, 1887, 1895, 1897-1901, 1904-1905 (Box 39, Folder 13)
  - Abstract of census returns of children in Pima County. 1873-1876 (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - School Census Marshall: Report. 1873-1904 (Box 40, Folder 2)
    1873: District No. 2, Sanford
    1873: District No. 3, Florence
    1873: District No. 4, San Pedro
    1874: District No. 2, Sanford
    1874: District No. 3, Florence
    1874: District No. 4, San Pedro
    1886-1887: District No. 1, Tucson
    1895-1896: District No. 6, Kenilworth
    ?: District No. 37, Oro
    1899-1900: District No. 29, Sahuarito
    1900-1901: District No. 1, Tucson
    1902-1903: District No. 1, Tucson
    1903-1904: District No. 1, Tucson
  - County Superintendent of Schools: Report to the Superintendent of Public Instruction regarding the annual school census. 1892-1893, 1893-1894, 1895-1896, 1897-1898 (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - Superintendent of Schools: Day Book of School Funds and Probate Court Docket. 1886-1887, 1883-1885 (Box 41)
    Record of receipts and disbursements for each district.
  - Superintendent of Schools: Minutes of meetings of the Board of Examiners of Pima County. 1889-1894 (Box 42)
  - Superintendent of Schools: Minutes of meetings of the Board of Trustees of School District No. 15. 1884-1886 (Box 43)
  - Superintendent of Schools: Record of Trustees in each school district. 1891-1896 (Box 44)
  - Superintendent of Schools: Quarterly financial report. July-September 1897 (Box 45)
  - Schools: Teachers' monthly reports from various districts. 1873-1875, 1891-1892, 1894-1896 (Box 46)
- Series VII: Miscellaneous (part 2), 1864-1884
  - Ore Shipments from Tucson. 1876-1877 (Box 47)
  - Recorder: Abstracts of unsatisfied mortgages. 1864-1876 (Box 48)
  - Tucson Gulf of California Railroad: Miscellaneous documents. 1882-1884 (Box 49)
- Series VIII: Tax Collector, 1871-1875
  - Tax Collector: License tax stubs. 1871, 1873-1875 (Box 50, Folder 1-4)
  - Tax Collector: Poll tax stubs. 1871-1872 (Box 50, Folder 5-6)
  - Tax Collector: Property tax stubs. 1871 (Box 50, Folder 7)
  - Tax Collector: Road tax. 1871 (Box 50, Folder 8)
- Series IX: Treasurer, 1865-1896
  - Treasurer: Receipts. 1865, 1868-1881, 1887, 1896 (Box 51)
    Issued by the Treasurer for:
    License and poll taxes collected by the Sheriff
    Fines and delinquent taxes issued by the Distract Attorney and Justice of the Peace
    Rent collected by the Sheriff and Clerk of the Board of Supervisors
    Tax roll issued by the Recorder
    Monies for School and General Funds directed by the Board of Supervisors
    Various other receipts dealing with county funds
  - Treasurer: Annual Report. 1873, 1876 (Box 52, Folder 1)
  - Treasurer: Monthly report of receipts and disbursements. 1890, 1896 (Box 52, Folder 2)
  - Treasurer: Quarterly report of receipts and disbursements. 1867-1887 (Box 52, Folder 3)
    Includes reports from:
    1867
    1869-1871
    January-March 1872
    1873-1876
    January-June 1877
    April-September 1878
    1879-1880
    July-September 1883
    Fragment for January-February 1887
  - Treasurer: Monthly statement of monies received. 1866-1872 (Box 52, Folder 4)
    Includes statements from:
    January-April 1866
    January-November 1867
    January-December 1869
    January-December 1870
    January-February, April, June-July 1871
    April 1872
  - Treasurer: Quarterly statement of receipts into the treasury. 1871-1876 (Box 52, Folder 5)
    1871
    1873
    January-June 1874
    1875
    1876
    Also July-September, no year given
- Series X: Election Returns, 1864-1902
  - Election returns including poll lists, tally lists, certificates of registration and other related material. 1864, 1870, 1874, 1876, 1878, 1880, 1890, 1902 (Box 53)